怎么回事？
发生什么事了？
What is it?
What happened?
你爸这下该没完没了了
lt just never stops
with your father.
他怎么了？
What'd he do?
他被评选为“年度先生”了
He was voted
Man of the Year.
年度先生？
Man of the Year?
《时代》杂志发什么神经了？
What has happened
to "Time" magazine?
不，是在他的俱乐部里
No, no.
At his lodge.
他的俱乐部发什么神经了？
What has happened
to his lodge?
噢，他们傻得要命
Oh, they're so stupid.
甚至不允许女士接近
Women aren't even
allowed near the place.
除非他们想要有人给他们筹办一场赞礼
Until they want one of us
to arrange a tribute or something.
－赞礼？
－是的
￡- Tribute?
￡- Yeah.
－要我们来做？
－唔～
￡- And we gotta go?
￡- Mm￡-hm.
那天我会生病
l got dibs on l'm sick
that night.
你就说要加班
You do some cop
overtime at work￡-￡-
就说猴子跑到公交车上了什么的
monkey on a bus
somewhere, yeah.
不，我倒是想去
No, no.
l want to go.
作为年度先生的儿子
是很光荣的一件事
lt's an honor to be son
of Man of the Year.
我甚至连
l don't even want
to be brother of guy
当年度先生的儿子的弟弟都不想
who wants to be son
of Man of the Year.
罗伯特的态度是对的
No, Robert has
the right attitude.
这对你爸爸是件大事
This is a big deal
for your father.
但我什么都不想做
And l want nothing
to do with it.
你什么意思？我以为
你会操办整件事
What do you mean? Thought you
had to organize the whole thing.
－噢，不！
－噢，是的
￡- Oh, no!
￡- Oh, yes.
你们两个来操办
你爸爸为此很兴奋呢
You two are gonna do this.
Your father's very excited.
他早就开始为此烦我了
He's already bothering
me about it.
爸爸已经知道了？
Dad knows about this?
现在评选年度先生已经不是什么秘密了
They don't surprise
the Man of the Year anymore.
所以他们才失去了上一届年度先生
That's how they lost
the last Man of the Year.
来吧，小家伙
我们一起来办
Come on, cubby,
we'll do it together.
爸爸一定会很高兴的
我们该做些什么？妈妈
lt will be nice for Dad.
What do we have to do, Mom?
－你教教我
－好的
￡- Come on, you tell me.
￡- Okay.
那个人做了报告
The guy said something
about a presentation
－还有些事先准备好的演说
－哪个人？
￡- or some prepared remarks.
￡- What guy?
我不清楚
高级白痴～
l don't know.
The Grand High ldiot.
雷蒙德，坐下
你们来办
All right, Raymond,
sit down, you're doing this.
－你们可以作首歌
－是啊
￡- You could do a song.
￡- Yeah.
还记得我很喜欢的那首吗？
You know that one number
l've always loved?
“南太平洋”
那些家伙穿着
From "South Pacific"
where the guy wears
草裙和椰子壳胸罩
the grass skirt
and the coconut bra?
是哦～
Yeah!
你平时在家里都干些什么啊！
What do you do
in that apartment?
早上好，家人们
Hello, family.
我看你是“年度椅子先生”
l believe you're
in the Chair of the Year.
祝贺你，爸爸！
真了不起！
Congratulations, Dad!
l think it's great!
谢谢，你们要知道
Thank you.
But you know...
我只不过是个
想努力超越自己的普通人
l'm just a simple man
who tried to make a difference.
我和你们一样
一次也只能穿一条裤子
l still put my pants
on one leg at a time.
是吗？我们什么时候才能盼到那个时候？
Yeah, and when can we
look forward to that?
嘿，这池子不错啊
是个放松的好地方
Hey, nice pool.
What a great hang￡-out.
－跟他们谈吧
－打扰一下，先生
￡- Let's talk to this guy over here.
￡- Excuse me, sir.
－能跟你谈谈吗？
－当然
￡- Could we talk to you for a second?
￡- Sure.
呃，我们想问你一些关于弗兰克・巴龙的问题
Uh, we'd like to ask you some questions
about Frank Barone.
开始吧
Shoot.
第一个问题：
Number one:
你为什么不穿衣服？
Why aren't you
wearing a bathing suit?
显然这是俱乐部的规定
lt's obviously
lodge policy.
这是这里的传统
lt's tradition.
－或许我们不该在这里摄像
－不，没关系
￡- Maybe we shouldn't film in here?
￡- No, no, it's fine.
我要开始了
l'll tell you what,
l'm gonna set up right here.
先做一下自我介绍
雷蒙德会采访你，知道了吗？
State your name and Raymond here
is gonna interview you, all right?
不，我不想采访
No, listen.
l don't want to interview.
我来拿摄像机
Let me hold
the camera.
快点，雷
你没看见他越来越冷了吗？
Come on, Ray.
Can't you see the guy's getting cold?
好吧
All right.
Here we go.
呃，开拍！
Uh, l don't know.
Action!
好吧，我现在和……
All right, l'm here
with, uh...
我和……
你刚说你叫什么名字？
l'm here with,
what'd you say your name was?
艾伯・沃奇则
但是人们都叫我子弹头
Abe Warchizer.
But everybody calls me Bullethead.
好吧……
All right...
子弹头，呃……
Bullethead, uh...
告诉我们你为什么喜欢弗兰克・巴龙？
just tell us why
you like Frank Barone?
我不喜欢弗兰克・巴龙
l don't like Frank Barone.
OK
Okay.
我现在能到池子里去了吗？
Can l get back
in the pool now?
好吧
Yeah, please.
那一定会伤到他的
That's gotta hurt.
该死，他不喜欢爸爸
Jeez, he doesn't
like Dad.
你担心子弹头说的话吗？
打扰了，先生
You're worried about what Bullethead
thinks? Excuse me, sir.
－你认识弗兰克・巴龙吗？
－那又怎样？
￡- You know Frank Barone, right?
￡- What of it?
我们在准备赞礼
你们推举他为年度先生
We're doing a tribute.
You guys elected him Man of the Year.
我们选了他？
We're down to him?
也许这些人并不十分了解爸爸
Maybe these guys
don't know Dad so well.
不，也许他们很了解
Yeah, maybe they do.
嘿看啊，那是他的牌友
Hey look!
There's his friends from poker.
嘿，盖文，斯坦！
Hey Garvin, Stan!
嘿，罗伯特
Hey, Robert!
嘿，雷也在这！
Hey, Ray's here!
嘿，盖文，你好吗？
嘿，斯坦
Hey, Garvin, hi.
How are you? Hi, Stan.
嘿，雷，你们要拍什么录像？
Hey, Ray, what's going
on with the video?
给爸爸准备赞礼
Well, it's for Dad's
tribute.
好极了，你们一起来，OK？
This is perfect.
You guys can do it together, okay?
准备好了？雷
开拍！
Ready, Ray?
And action!
开始转了？
lt's rolling?
是啊，我们现在和盖文……
Yeah, okay, all right.
We're here with Garvin￡-￡-
嘿，弗兰克！
你还欠我50块钱！
Hey, Frank!
You owe me 50 bucks!
你答应还我的！
但到现在还没还！
You gave me your word!
l ain't heard from you since!
你躲了我1年半了！听到了吗？
You've been ducking me
for a year and a half! You hear me?!
50块钱还是小事！
50 bucks is nothing!
你还把我的车撞了一个坑！
How about the dent
you put in my car!
还说那不是你干的！
You told me
it wasn't you!
但我有目击证人！
我还有帐单！
l have eyewitnesses!
And l have a bill!
要是我现在有口袋就好了
我一定会随身带着的！
l wish l had pockets
'cause l'd carry it with me!
等着瞧！
Wait right here!
你这个骗子！
You're a liar!
骗子！听到了吗？
A liar!
You hear me?
骗子！
Liar!
谢谢，谢谢
Thank you.
嘿雷，很高兴再见到你！
Hey Ray, it's really nice
to see you again, you know?
保重，朋友！
Take care there, buddy!
向你妈妈问好！
Hey, say hi
to your mom!
我们怎么办？
What are we
going to do?
不知道
l don't know.
也许我们可以把一些片段剪辑一下
Maybe we can piece something
together in editing, you know?
打扰一下，先生们
现在正式开拍
Excuse me, guys.
Just start rolling.
嗨，请允许我们问几个问题
Hi, uh, we just want to ask
a few questions if you don't mind.
呃……
Uh...
你们觉得……
how do you feel
about...
巧克力怎么样？
chocolate?
－太棒了！
－我的最爱
￡- Really good.
￡- My favorite.
很美味，总是很美味！
Delicious.
Always delicious.
－当然，我很喜欢……
－弗兰克・巴龙
￡- Sure, l like￡-￡-
￡- Frank Barone.
－永远都不嫌多
－这是我的最爱
￡- l can't get enough.
￡- lt's my favorite.
唔～～～
Mmm￡-mm￡-mm.
－我的妻子也很喜欢……
－弗兰克・巴龙
￡- My wife goes nuts for￡-￡-
￡- Frank Barone.
天赐的礼物！
A wonderful gift.
－谁会不喜欢……
－弗兰克・巴龙
￡- Who doesn't like￡-￡-
￡- Frank Barone.
唔～唔～
Mmm￡-mm￡-mm.
－爸爸，怎么了？
－这算什么颁奖礼？
￡- Come on, Dad. What are you doing?
￡- That was a tribute?
－怎么？你不喜欢？
－傻死了
￡- What, you didn't like it?
￡- lt was stupid!
而且太短了
And it was so short!
我们用的是那种……
Yeah, well, we kinda
went with a fast
快速MTV的剪辑手法
MTv kind of editing.
我不喜欢
Well l didn't get it!
还有科莱利说他喜欢我裹着糖粉热呼呼的
是什么意思？
And what's with Correlli saying
he likes me hot with marshmallows?
－我叫你把那一段剪掉的！
－但我觉得很可爱！
￡- l told you to get rid of that!
￡- lt was cute!
弗兰克，你在干什么啊？
Frank, what are you doing?
走吧，我们回家
Come on, we're going home.
你说什么呢？今天是你的大日子
What are you talking about?
This is your big night!
已经不是什么大日子了，走吧
lt's not so big anymore.
Let's go.
你连牛排都没吃完
You didn't even finish
your steak.
我不饿！
l'm not hungry!
我们真应该打扮成小妞的！
Should've dressed
like broads!
别这个样子！
Would you stop?
孩子们没做错什么
The boys did nothing wrong.
你不是想要他们给你准备一个赞礼吗？
他们准备了！
You wanted them to make you
a tribute, they made you a tribute.
我等不及要听我的颂词了！
l can't wait
for my eulogy!
你真不该就那样离开
那是孩子们特意为你准备的夜晚
You still don't walk out on an evening
your sons planned for you.
汤姆・崔凡雅克的赞礼有37分钟！
Tom Trevonyak got a tribute
that lasted 37 minutes!
他们把他的整个人生都拍了进去
The guys made a whole
video on his life
盛大的演说，温馨的笑声
表达他们有多爱他
with big speeches and laughs
and how much they love him.
他们还录了一段精彩的舞蹈
And they did a big,
wonderful music thing
每个人都打扮得像个小妞
where they all
dressed up like broads.
罗比本来也打算那么穿的
Well Robbie was ready
to dress up.
糟透了！他们做得糟透了！
That stunk, what they did!
All right?
我知道赞礼应该是怎样的！
l know a tribute!
这个家不再欢迎他们了
They're not welcomed
in this house anymore!
－真的吗？
－没错
￡- Oh, really?
￡- That's correct!
－这么说他们让你失望了？
－是的
￡- So they let you down?
￡- Yes!
－那你那些俱乐部的朋友呢？
－他们怎么了？
￡- What about your buddies at the lodge?
￡- What about them!
你怎么不想想
如果他们说了你很多好话
Don't you think if they
had said something great
雷蒙德和罗比怎么可能不拍下来？
that Raymond and Robbie
would have put it in?
这才是真正让你烦恼的吧？
lsn't that what's
really bothering you?
“用泡菜做成脚趾”
& l've got pickles
for toes &
“芥菜做成鼻子……”
& And a rutabaga nose... &
弗兰克，你在干嘛？
Frank, what are you doing?
看电视
l'm watching.
“樟树叶子做头发，再把甜瓜放在……：
& Sassafras hair
and a melon under there... &
把它关掉
Come on.
Shut that off, please.
安静，我听不见了
Quiet!
l can't hear.
你关不关，弗兰克？
Would you shut it, Frank?
“我是个蔬菜人，你可以把我吃掉。
尝尝我的手……”
& l'm the veggie wedge man
and you can eat me, try my hand. &
蠢玩意～
Stupid crap!
知道吗？我打算退出那个俱乐部
You know what?
l'm quitting that lodge.
－太好了
－你说太好了是什么意思？
￡- Good.
￡- What do you mean, good?
那是个白痴俱乐部
lt's a stupid lodge.
里面都是些脑筋秀逗的老头
lt's full of crotchety
old men who think
认为人生最大的享受就是
赤身裸体地流汗和咳嗽
the greatest luxury in life
is sweating naked and coughing.
而你总是一味地抱怨他们
And all you ever do
is complain about them.
你以前怎么不说？
Well why didn't you
say something before?
因为那会让你滚远些
lt gets you
out of the house.
走吧，睡觉去
Come on.
Let's go to bed.
－嘿
－什么？
￡- Hey.
￡- What?
你……你会说什么？
What￡-￡- what would
you say?
什么？
What?
你会在赞礼里说什么？
What would you say
in a tribute?
什么意思？
What do you mean?
你会在我的赞礼里说什么？
What would you say
in a tribute to me?
我不知道，弗兰克
Well, l don't know,
Frank.
他们没问过我
They didn't ask me.
OK
Okay.
我会说……
l would say...
他是我结婚42年的丈夫
he's been my husband
for 42 years.
我们有两个棒儿子
That we have two
wonderful boys together
还有三个漂亮的孙子
and three beautiful
grandchildren.
不是吗？
lsn't that right?
就这样？
That's it?
还没说完呢
Let me finish.
他一直陪伴在我们身边
And that he's always
been there for us
支持着我们
and been a good
provider.
尽管我们时不时地争吵
And that even though
we squabble every now and then,
我知道
l know that...
他就是我要的那个人
he's the one for me.
尽管有很多不爽，但我会忍着的
And whatever l did
to deserve him, l'll live with.
说得好！我喜欢这种幽默
l like that!
With the humor, yeah.
现在，我能问你几个问题吗？
Now, can l ask
you something?
－走吧，我们该睡觉了
－不，不。别这样，弗兰克
￡- Come on, let's go to bed.
￡- No, no, come on, Frank!
我们在聊天！
We were talking!
－我累了，我要去睡觉
－噢，当然了
￡- l'm tired. l'm going to bed.
￡- Oh, sure!
你从我这儿得到了你想要的
现在要去睡觉了
Now you got what you needed
from me and now you're going to sleep.
已经不是新鲜事了
What else is new?
你到底想干嘛？
What do you want?
我想和你沟通，弗兰克
l want to have
a conversation, Frank.
我想和你说说话
l want to talk to you.
这个要求过分吗？
ls that asking so much?
我就知道会这样
l know where this is going.
到这里来
Here, here.
坐下
Sit down here,
please.
一个男人究竟能承受多少“沟通”？
How much talking
can a guy take?
谢谢
Thank you.
现在……
Now...
要是你，会怎么赞颂我呢？
What would your tribute
for me be?
－嗯？
－这太傻了吧？
￡- Well?
￡- This is stupid.
你刚才问我的时候怎么不觉得傻？
lt wasn't stupid
when you just asked me!
我现在意识到傻了
Yes it was!
l know realize how stupid it was!
我刚才给了你一个中听的、慷慨的回答
是不是？
Well l gave you a very lovely
and generous answer, didn't l?
不是吗？
Well didn't l?
好吧
All right!
你在等什么啊？
What are you
getting ready for?
我又不是给你洗礼
l'm not anointing
you here.
你可是难得对我说几句好话的
Well, it isn't every day you say
nice things about me.
那是因为你难得强迫我说
Well it's not every day
that you force me!
噢，别这样！弗兰克
Oh, stop it, Frank!
快点啊，你会说什么？
Come on!
What were you going to say?
－ 你说话唾沫星子乱溅！
－ 噢，够了！
￡- Sometimes you spit when you talk.
￡- Oh, that's it!!
－够了！
－嘿，我说什么了？
￡- That's it!
￡- Hey, what did l say! Come on!
你是我最需要的人
You're the one for me!
你想知道为什么人们不喜欢你吗？
弗兰克
You want to know why people
don't love you, Frank?
你想知道吗？
因为你什么都不肯付出
You want to know?
You offer them nothing. That's right.
你得付出爱，弗兰克，才能得到爱
You have to give love,
Frank, to get it.
但你从不愿付出
And you have never
ever been willing to do that!
你只是一味地索取、索取
You just take
and take and take
还期望每个人都忍受你的可恶
and expect everybody
to accept your obnoxious
就像茅坑里的石头！
horse's ass
of a personality!
每个人都得容忍你
And everybody has to put up
with it because it's you!
你知道最悲哀的是什么吗？
You know what the sad
part is?
你的身边是一群爱你的家人
You are surrounded by family
who happen to love you anyway.
而你却把他们推得远远的
And you push them away.
你把我们都推得远远的
You push us all away.
但从今以后，不再需要了
You don't have
to push anymore.
你真不打算和我谈了？
You're not gonna talk
to me about this?
弗兰克？！
Frank?!
婚姻不应该是这样的
弗兰克
This is not a marriage,
Frank!
婚姻应该是两个人分担、交流！
A marriage is two people
sharing things, talking!
假如出现了问题，应该好好沟通！
And if they have a problem,
they talk about it!
你不能坐在那里，面无表情地看着
你的妻子离去
You don't just sit there
and wait for the other one to go away!
你能在任何地方找到的东西……
Anything you'll find
anywhere else.
刚才谁说三明治？
Did someone say
sandwiches?
我！
Yes!
噢！
Oh.
我们得谈谈！
We're gonna talk
about this.
噢，他妈的～！
Oh crap!
－ 我的妈呀！
－ 别这样，弗兰克
￡- Jeez!
￡- Oh, stop it, Frank!
某人想睡觉，却被艺妓袭击了
A guy wants to go to bed,
he gets attacked by a kabuki.
够了！
Oh, stop it!
好吧
All right.
现在说吧
Now you talk
to me.
好吧，听着
我……
All right.
Look, l, uh...
知道孩子们已经尽力了
我知道，呃……
know the boys did their best.
l know, uh...
人们不喜欢我，是我自己的过错
it's my own stupid fault
people aren't crazy about me
我对大家很抱歉
and l'm sorry
to everybody.
你那么说是为了敷衍我吧？
You're just saying that
so l'll leave you alone.
你就不能对我说几句中听的话么？
You still can't think of anything
nice to say about me?
我枕着它睡觉怎么样？
How about l
sleep on it?
真是可笑！
lt's all jokes.
弗兰克，你在干什么？
别，我有用的
Frank, what are you doing?
No, no, l need that.
弗兰克！
Frank!
弗兰……
Fr￡-￡-
我比较喜欢你脸上没有这些破玩意儿
l like you better
without the crap on your face.
OK？
Okay?
你应该试着每天都对我说一些像这样的话
You should try and say something
like that to me every day.
我会试的
l'll try.
嘿，呃……
Hey, uh￡-￡-
什么？
What?
我是年度先生
Well, l am
Man of the Year.
没错，你就是的
Yes, you are.
我现在要努力摆脱“年度一次先生”
And l'm looking to move
up from Man Once a Year.
瞧？幽默吧？
See?
With the humor.
想不想去睡了？
Want to go to bed?
我还……
l just, uh￡-￡-
亲爱的，怎么了？
Oh, honey, what?
你什么都没做错
You didn't do
anything wrong.
我喜欢那个短片
l liked that tribute.
让我胃口大开
Made me hungry.
我不知道
l don't know.
也许我应该道歉的
Maybe l should
apologize.
知道吗？
l￡-￡- you know what?
我打个电话过去，感觉会好很多的
We'll all feel better
if l just call.
－他们不在家？
－不知道
￡- What, are they not home?
￡- l don't know.
没人接……
哈喽，爸爸？
Nobody's answering.
Hello! Yeah, Dad?
你还好吗？
Are you okay?
不，我只是……
Yeah.
No, l just￡-￡-
我想说……关于那个赞礼
l wanna￡-￡-
about the tribute.
－你知道现在是几点了吗？
－好吧！OK
￡- Do you know what time it is?!
￡- All right! Okay!
我只是……我……
好吧，好吧。对不起
l just￡-￡- l didn't￡-￡-
all right, okay, sorry.
他现在打来干什么？
What's he calling
now for?
不知道
l don't know.
有时候我真希望他们不住在街对面
You know, sometimes l wish
they didn't live across the street.
翻译：LISA DOLL
yukii45@hotmail.com
谢谢观赏